<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Poland. Wherein is truly inlarged the occasion, progression, and interception of the Turks formidable threatning of Europe. And particularly, the inuading of the kingdome of Poland. With many severall repulses he hath receiued from that braue and military nation: euen to this present moneth of October: as is truly collected out of the originall. Published by authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.35B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.114.d.5[17]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99893072</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99893072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">193603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14980)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 193603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C27:1[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Poland. Wherein is truly inlarged the occasion, progression, and interception of the Turks formidable threatning of Europe. And particularly, the inuading of the kingdome of Poland. With many severall repulses he hath receiued from that braue and military nation: euen to this present moneth of October: as is truly collected out of the originall. Published by authority.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>imprinted by F. K. for B. D. and William Lee, and are to bee sold at his shop in Fleet-street, at the signe of the golden Buck, neere Serieants Inne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cf. STC 18507.35A which has imprint date 1621</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ (-A1)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poland --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:193603:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:193603:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEWES FROM POLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN</hi> IS TRVLY IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LARGED THE OCCASION, <hi>PROGRESSION, AND INTERCEP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Turks formidable threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND PARTICVLARLY, the inuading of the Kingdome</hi> of POLAND.</p>
            <p>WITH MANY SEVERALL RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes he hath receiued from that braue and mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Nation: euen to this preſent moneth <hi>of October: as is truly collected out of the Originall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quid verba quaeris?</l>
               <l>Veritas odit moras.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Seneca in Oedippo.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>F. K.</hi> for <hi>B. D.</hi> and <hi>William Lee,</hi> and are to bee fold at his ſhop in Fleet-ſtreet, at the ſigne of the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> neere Serieants Inne. 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:193603:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:193603:2"/>
            <head>NEWES FROM POLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the greatneſſe of the Empire of <hi>Turky,</hi> and the warlike concuſſions where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they haue affrighted both <hi>Perſia</hi> and <hi>Europe:</hi> you may conſider it thus in the generall, that <hi>Mahomet,</hi> the author of their Religion and <hi>Alcaron,</hi> enioyned the race of <hi>Othoman</hi> to two ſpeciall things. Firſt, The one was the propagation of the Empire by ſome memorable attempt of war. Secondly, The other, the glorification of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by ſome remarkeable action of peace, or ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendous ſtructure of amazement.</p>
            <p>Touching the firſt; It is too apparant, that their territories extend to the <hi>Aſian</hi> and <hi>Africane</hi> ſhores, from <hi>Trebizond,</hi> in the bottome of the blacke Sea, to <hi>Argier,</hi> neighbouring the Straites of <hi>Gibralter,</hi> very neere ſixe thouſand Engliſh miles, beſide the poſſeſſion of <hi>Greece,</hi> and her Ilands, with his intruſion into <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and dilacerating the peace of many Nations: They haue likewiſe as an
<pb facs="tcp:193603:3"/>auxiliary friend, the great <hi>Tartar Chrim,</hi> from whoſe Anceſtars <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> proceeded, who though himſelfe proued a great enemy to <hi>Turkes,</hi> yet doth <hi>Tartar Chrim</hi> boaſt of affinity to the firſt <hi>Scythian Othoman,</hi> ſo that if his direct line ſhould faile, he challengeth the proximity of Succeſſion, and inioying the proſperity of theſe large Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> for which purpoſe hee keepeth correſpondency with the <hi>Turke,</hi> and at his appoyntment ſendeth 100000. <hi>Tartars</hi> to aſſiſt him in his enterpriſes, whereby the <hi>Turkes</hi> haue many times great multitudes of men, and good ſucceſſe in their attempts: For they haue preuailed both againſt <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Christians,</hi> poſſeſſing at this houre the Metropolitan City of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in <hi>Aſia, Grand Cairo</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> and are indeed tranſported with an inſulting brauery, that they are a people deſigned of God, to bee the principall Nation of the earth, and a ſcourge to whip the ſinners of the world.</p>
            <p>Touching the glorification of their Religion; who knowes not, that either hath been conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> or would be conuerſant with the ſtories of former times, that the <hi>Almora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, Solimanna, Sophia,</hi> and diuers other <hi>Moſques,</hi> be not onely oſtentous edifices and Churches of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, but workes of charity, and obſeruant ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe: yea, as we call it, money laid out <hi>ad pios v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus?</hi> I ſpeake not of <hi>Iobs</hi> Tombe, nor many other ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred places, wherein theſe Princes, to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate their opinion of a Deity, and care to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:193603:3"/>
               <hi>Mahumetan</hi> conſtitutions, imployed their time, and wealth, ſuperſtitiouſly conceiting ſome merit in their obedience; and that the ioyes of Paradiſe ſhould be augmented, as they augmented their piety on earth: nay, you ſhall reade in that wonderfull hiſtory of <hi>Soliman</hi> the Magnificent; and the faire, though dangerous <hi>Roxalana,</hi> that ſhe contriued her manumiſſion, and ſo obtained to be <hi>Empreſſe,</hi> vnder a diſſimuled ſanctity, and holy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to the building of a Church in honour of the <hi>Prophet, and glory</hi> of Religion. In a word, you ſhall find, that by this occaſion, the principall <hi>Muf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> with the Doctors of the Law, haue more acceſſe to the <hi>Emperour,</hi> and open a larger heart of ſecrets, then either <hi>Viceer,</hi> or <hi>Baſhaw.</hi> Yea the <hi>Emperour,</hi> be he neuer ſo warlike, or vicious, ſtandeth more in awe of their prohibitions, then the reuolts or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies of the tumultuary <hi>Ianiſaries,</hi> by whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, as you reade of <hi>Hercules</hi> and <hi>Atlas</hi> ſupporting the heauens, this great frame of <hi>Monarchy</hi> is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, and kept ſecure, from any daring hands to diſ-ioynt the ſame: and thus in generall.</p>
            <p>But if you would more particularly be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the motiues, and actiue terrifying the Kingdome of <hi>Poland,</hi> and other confederate Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prouinces, wee muſt needs fetch the ſtory a little from the beginning, and ſo draw it downe to theſe moderne times, wherein the braue <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> and the hopefull Prince his Sonne, haue prooued the ſonnes of <hi>Mars,</hi> and regiſtred their renownes vpon the record of honour, and filled vp the tally
<pb facs="tcp:193603:4"/>of exployts with their vvorthineſſe.</p>
            <p>Know then, that vvhile Sir <hi>Thomas Glouer</hi> was his Maieſties of <hi>Englands</hi> Embaſſador at <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> there was reſident in his houſe, one <hi>Gaſparo Gratiano,</hi> in the nature of a <hi>Drogaman,</hi> who was of <hi>Austria,</hi> and ſo a Subiect to <hi>Rodulphus,</hi> Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> but at laſt a ſeruant to the Prince of <hi>Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauia:</hi> that Prince, I meane, that came into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and had gracious intertainement with the King and his Nobles: that Prince, vvho vvas diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed of his inheritance through the povver of Competitors: that Prince, vvhoſe Mother I haue ſeene poorely ſolliciting the Embaſſador at <hi>Constantinople</hi> for reliefe: that Prince, vvho vvas vvith the ſame <hi>Gaſparo</hi> impriſoned in the ſeuen Towers, for complayning of the Viceer, who tooke part vvith his Competitor: that Prince, vvho yet eſcaped, and vvas faine to flee for ſuccour to all the Princes of <hi>Europe:</hi> that Prince, vvho returned from <hi>England</hi> vvith ſufficient revvard, and credit for ten thouſand Dollers among our Marchants. In a word, that Prince, vvho couertly came from <hi>Venice</hi> to <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and ſo engaged Sir <hi>Thomas Glouer,</hi> that hee had reaſon to complaine of the Viceers oppoſition, and the neglect of his ovvne fortune. For as it ſhould ſeeme, he had taken vp ſo much money to aſſiſt him, that he almoſt loſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and made a great vertue vmbragious vvith the malignity of time.</p>
            <p>Yet doth that Prince aduenture to <hi>Moldauia,</hi> determining to re-integrate his fortune, by raiſing
<pb facs="tcp:193603:4"/>of factions. But it ſhould ſeeme ſtill <hi>Nemeſis in Tergo.</hi> For his aduerſaries vvere ſo ſtrengthened by the <hi>Viceers</hi> fauour at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> that there vvent out a ſtrange Edict from the <hi>Grand ſignieur,</hi> both to haue a ceſſation of the vvarre, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh the Vſurper in the poſſeſſion. Thus fled the Prince once againe into <hi>Poland,</hi> and vvas pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed reliefe, yea, ſo forvvard in returning home, that ſome companies of foote, and troopes of Horſe vvere ready to march in his behalfe.</p>
            <p>While theſe things vvere thus acted on the ſtage of variety in <hi>Moldauia, Signieur Gaſparo Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiano</hi> imployed in <hi>Venice</hi> by Sir <hi>Thomas Glouer,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes to <hi>Constantinople;</hi> but finding that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors fortunes vvere, as it were obſcured with ſome cloud of diſturbance, he went another way to worke to winde vp the pullies of his owne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement, either by force, or policy, in which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution all things were ſo auſpicious vnto him, that he was ſuddenly ſent vvith letters to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of <hi>Germany</hi> from the <hi>Grand ſignieur,</hi> which was ſomewhat wondred at in reſpect of his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and former ſeruile imployment, till it was publikely knowne that his owne brother was a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negado Chawſe,</hi> and in good account with the <hi>Viceer,</hi> yea, one of his ſiſters (as he told me him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) was taken priſoner comming as a Pilgrime to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and ſo brought to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> but whether reſerued for the <hi>Turkes</hi> vſe, or ſome <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> he could not tell.</p>
            <p>In the meane while, Sir <hi>Thomas Glouer</hi> is recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:193603:5"/>into <hi>England,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Paul Pindar,</hi> who had been Conſull at <hi>Petraſſe</hi> and <hi>Aleppo,</hi> as many yeeres commorant in thoſe parts, was confirmed his Maieſties Embaſſadour in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in whoſe time the former <hi>Gaſparo Gratiano</hi> returnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the great Citty, and was imployed into <hi>Moldauia</hi> by the Viceer, either as an ouerſeer of the actions of that Prouince, or as a new aduerſary to the vnfortunate Prince his Maſter, who at laſt was there miſchieuouſly poyſoned amongſt them, or as ſome will haue it, abſolute gouernour, till the true titles might appeare, and the controuerſies be determined.</p>
            <p>How he behaued himſelfe, I will not diſpute, nor conſtantly maintaine, that he dealt treacherouſly with the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> certifying vnder hand, that contrary to the peace contracted with the <hi>Grand ſignieur,</hi> he ſupported the pirats of the black Sea, and the inhabitants of <hi>Bugdonia,</hi> the inteſtine broyles of <hi>Moldauia,</hi> the incurſions of many <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks,</hi> whereby the <hi>Turke</hi> was then much exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt <hi>Poland,</hi> and a manifeſt cloud of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe hung ouer all thoſe Countries apparantly. But this I am ſure of, that his Maieſties Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of <hi>Poland,</hi> Leigier at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> had neither ſo gracious audience as he was wont, nor ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity as the priuiledges of Embaſſadors preſumed on. For preſently the <hi>Grand ſignieur</hi> exclaymed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them all in fury and diſpleaſure, and when there was forcible intimation indeed concerning the buſines of <hi>Moldauia,</hi> and the many claymes to
<pb facs="tcp:193603:5"/>the Principality by factious Lords, he not onely gaue commaundement to ouer-runne that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, but to teach <hi>Poland</hi> it ſelfe a new leſſon of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> durſt be auxiliary to a petty Prouince, againſt ſo mighty a Monarke and greateſt Prince in the world: nor ended it thus in a kinde of ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der inuectiue, but the threatnings had tearmes of oſtentation, beſides the exprobrating their perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſneſſe, yea, the letters had wonderfull titles, and far-fetcht denominations, the Embaſſies, mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of profaneneſſe, and preſumption of ouer-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Europe;</hi> and all this was done in the life of <hi>Achmate,</hi> though for the time the whole frame of this conceiued diſpleaſure proued a Babyloniſh Tovver, and ended onely in confuſion of Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: For as yet more then the cuſtomary breaking out of the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> of <hi>Bogdonia,</hi> and the territories about the blacke Sea, there vvas no mayne Army on foot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but onely certaine preparatiues to a fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovving warre. For as if hee would leaue his rage hereditary, he commanded the principall <hi>Mufti</hi> and Doctors of the Law to remember this charge to his Sonne, and put him in minde of the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: which accordingly vvith filiall obedience he performed indeed, and brought out the furies of his vengeance to act that part, which they haue now played in thoſe Countries. But becauſe many remarkeable things happened in the death of <hi>Ach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate,</hi> before this young <hi>Phaeton</hi> came to guide and manage the Horſes of this Monarchies Chariot, giue mee leaue to inſiſt a little vpon them, and
<pb facs="tcp:193603:6"/>modell out this relation to ſome forme of pleaſure and contentment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Achmate</hi> comming to the Empire at 15. yeeres old, remained in the ſame, till he was almoſt thirty, in which time pleaſure ſurfetted on eaſe, and eaſe had ſuch changes of wantonneſſe, that hee ſeemed weary with the continuance of delight: for <hi>Sarda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>napalus</hi> came ſhort of him for abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, and variety of luxurie: ſo that if it bee true, that <hi>Voluptates commendat rarior vſus,</hi> it muſt needs follow, that to play thus continually, proued as te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to him as to worke; and to gurmandize thus without ceſſation, muſt needs raiſe rather a loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſſe then ſatisfaction. In briefe, he had ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiues &amp; children, that, in a maner, he forgot the the glory of his Family, &amp; the proſecution of glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enterpriſes, giuing himſelfe ouer to the <hi>Syrens</hi> incantation of <hi>Luſt</hi> and laſciuiouſneſſe: in the heate of which outrage, he determined to kill his brother <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> a Prince of great expectation, whom, as yet, ſome ſupernaturall prouidence had preſerued from death: But now to colour his pretences, ſuch was the law, ſuch was the cuſtome, nay, ſuch was the neceſſity of preſeruation, that as Nature teacheth all creatures the way of ſecurity; ſo had Policy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed theſe Princes by this one <hi>Machiauelia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> trick to preuent miſchiefes, inſurrections, factions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions, murthers, and all ſuch affrightings that make Princes vnhappy, if they be once put in feare indeed. This made <hi>Damocles</hi> that he could eate no meate, when hee ſaw the ſword ready to fall vpon
<pb facs="tcp:193603:6"/>him, that hung ouer his head by a horſe haire. This made the Emperour tell his flatterer, that if he knew what cares were the Companions of his Crowne, he would not take it vp, though it lay in his way as a donation of Fortune. This made <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi> truſt none but his daughter, to burne off his haire with nutſhels: and this made <hi>Achmate</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the cuſtome of his <hi>Progenitors,</hi> by remouing all the cauſes of terrour and ſuſpition, though the life of his brethren payed for it.</p>
            <p>But what ſayes the Poet? <hi>Multa cadunt inter ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licem ſupremáque labra.</hi> So as this iolly Prince was running away with the apprehenſion of his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſetting downe a determinate houre for the ſtrangling of Prince <hi>Muſtapha</hi> his brother, the night before the period of his <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> a fearfull Viſion diuerted him from the enterpriſe, and a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full voyce ecchoed in his eares, that there could bee no Religion in murther; and thoſe ſacrifices which the Tyrants made in former times, of blood and humane fleſh, were the cauſes of the ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſtation of their Monarchies; yea, vtter loſſe of body and ſoule to the Princes themſelues.</p>
            <p>Little thought the great <hi>Turke</hi> to haue found a greater Greatneſſe in his ſleepe, and leſſe did hee ſuſpect that there was ſuch a God aboue to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termand the gods on the earth. But ſo predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was his ouer-ruling <hi>Genius</hi> at this time, and ſo tractable his obedience, that the very next day hee ſent for the principall <hi>Mufty,</hi> ſome Doctors of the Law, and <hi>Scander Baſhaw,</hi> who was delegated <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:193603:7"/>againſt the <hi>Polonians:</hi> To whom hee imparted the apparition, and of whom hee receiued ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſortable to the flattering of Princes; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnſeaſonable, becauſe his ſoule was touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſome rough hands, &amp; he wiſely conſidered there was more to bee looked after, then a preſent greatneſſe, or flouriſhing tyranny: whereupon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in their preſence he ſends for his brother, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth his <hi>Mutes,</hi> who were the officers of death, alloweth him a Gard of <hi>Capogies,</hi> appoynteth him a <hi>Caska,</hi> or Banqueting-houſe by himſelfe, and at laſt preuaileth thus with his owne great heart, that he venteth out theſe ſpeeches:</p>
            <p>Brother, ariſe, (for you muſt know, that all men comming to tractate with the Emperour, vſe à kind of ſlauiſh proſtitution, till, out of his free Prince lineſſe, he grace them with a new fauour.) You are not, I am ſure, ignorant of this ſecret o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> State, this law of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> this policy of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this meanes of our ſecurity, that when wee haue children of our owne, no brothers muſt liue to diſquiet them, nor any blockes bee caſt in their way to the race of Soueraignty, which may either ſtartle vs in our reſolutions, or bee vmbragious to their tenderneſſe by any attempt, or ſuſpition of treaſon: therefore was I reſolued to wrap you vp into the Cypreſſe cheſts of your predeceſſors; not ſo much in imitation of cuſtome, to which in a manner our fathers chained their liues and actions, as confirmation of my owne iudgement, not to commit ſuch a <hi>ſolleciſme</hi> in my Soueraignty, as to
<pb facs="tcp:193603:7"/>leaue a hand vncut off, which might, by way of audaciouſneſſe, caſt defiance in the face of an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, or ſow the ſeeds of turbulency, to choke vp the good corne of peace and quietneſſe: but ſure, thou haſt found ſome friend, whom none can finde, but by the purity of life, and deuotion of prayer: he hath told me in thy behalfe, There is no Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in blood. For as that ſtone-building cannot ſtand, which is ſet vp with vntempered morter: ſo cannot their liues proſper, who carowſe the receits that are mingled with death, or reuenge.</p>
            <p>Therefore liue, nay therefore raigne, and when the thred of my life is ſpun, which is now a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on the wheele of Deſtiny, looke you ſtep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the chaire of controll. Remember the <hi>Othoman</hi> glory, and let my abhorred courſe of life be a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto thee, that ſurquedry and effeminateneſſe be the onely clogs to a generous minde, and barre vp the gates euen in the inſide, to keepe Princes out of the Palace of Honour and renowne. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that though Monarkes would liue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controll; yet there are no ſuch enemies to the flouriſhings of Gouernment, as to ſport before them with the tripping <hi>Faeries</hi> of flattery, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate reſpect, vvhereby they ſhall either looke vvith ouer-big countenances, or ſpeake vvith ouer-big voyces to the ſubiect, or elſe giue vvay to ſuch by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvayes of authority, that if they may bee brought backe to looke vvheron they haue trod, they vvould ſtop their noſes at the filthy ordure of mud and ovvſe, vvhen yet they might haue gone in the
<pb facs="tcp:193603:8"/>ſmooth and ſweete tract of a more pleaſant and ſafer walke. Remember my children, that are Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by blood, and ſhould haue beene thy Maſters by birth-right: but they are too young to rule themſelues, and too great to bee ouer-ruled by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: nay, the <hi>Othoman</hi> glory muſt not be ſhared amongſt a troope of dependants, nor the Chariot wheeles of our Maieſty be daſhed with the daring approches of ſuch horſes, as muſt needs bedirty vs more then our owne flingings or wantonneſſe. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy ſelfe, that art, as it were pulled out of the iawes of death; and if it be a benefit to liue, or a bleſſing to liue gloriouſly, let it be thy vertue to be thankfull, and my good Fortune, that I impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this benefit to ſo worthy a man. To conclude, remember our God, and let not policy, like <hi>Prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi> his Vulture, gnaw vpon the heart of religion; but when thou ſeeſt any ſtart aſide from honeſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, be ſure he is either an hypocrite, or facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Keepe thy ſelfe therefore as cloſe to purity as thou canſt, and neither neglect publike meetings, nor priuate ſequeſtration, but take heed of ſeruing of God for priuate reſpects: For that God which doth giue vs bread, will giue vs ſtones, and turne our heauen into braſſe, and earth into iron, if wee doe not ſerue him for loue, and come to him with cheerfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>When he had made an end, hee ſent for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Viceers</hi> and <hi>Baſhawes,</hi> and adiured them to the ratification of his will: ſo his brother was diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to his Palace deſigned, and they diſcharged till
<pb facs="tcp:193603:8"/>they were recalled: but hee neuer troubled them more: for very ſhortly after, he yeelded to the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the great Commander of Princes, and gaue way to the alteration that followed in the State, yet for the time, with one generall conſent and vnanimity they inueſted the Princely <hi>Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> with the Diadem, in which he remained qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly a while, as if they made a conſcience of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringing the will of the dead, and were reſolued to admit of his vertue, that muſt needs adde glory to the Empire.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Scander Baſhaw</hi> perceiuing his owne autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity much diminiſhed by this tranſlation, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting another manner of greatneſſe, if hee might be aduanced to be <hi>Viceer</hi> vnder a younger Prince, intimated againſt the new Emperour, that hee was too much addicted to peace and ſobriety, and his coole ſpirit muſt needs draw on ſtrange inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences vpon the Empire; but in truth, he watched all opportunity to conuerſe with the children of <hi>Achmate,</hi> and found the liuely <hi>Oſman,</hi> or <hi>Othoman,</hi> being eight or nine yeeres old, ſo forward, and ſprightfull, that he durſt aske him, to his amaze, if he were not his fathers eldeſt ſonne: yea, he inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected ſuch ſtrange queſtions and demands, that the <hi>Baſhawes</hi> were already afraid they had done ſomething vniuſtifiable, and which muſt be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with no leſſe then the loſſe of their liues.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he reſolued on an alteration, and ſo conferred with the <hi>Viceer</hi> and principall <hi>Mufty,</hi> about the towardlineſſe of the young Prince, and
<pb facs="tcp:193603:9"/>ſaw no remedy for their ſecurity, but to depoſe <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha</hi> againe, &amp; make <hi>Oſman</hi> Emperour: to which, when none of that Councell and faction durſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, they preſently gaue the <hi>Ianiſaries</hi> a donatiue in the name of young <hi>Oſman,</hi> ſtored the <hi>Helleſpont</hi> with many Gallies, diſmiſſed certaine <hi>Tartarians,</hi> which were to goe into <hi>Bogdonia,</hi> and were not to be tolerated till the tumult was appeaſed, ſent for diuers <hi>Sanſacks</hi> and <hi>Timatriots</hi> to attend the young Emperour, and vnder-hand filled the great City with ſouldiers, ere <hi>Muſtapha</hi> could coniecture that they intended ſo waighty a buſineſſe, as the depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a Prince.</p>
            <p>But when all things were ready, and all men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, that were acquainted with the conſpiracy, <hi>Scander Baſhaw</hi> brought out the young <hi>Oſman</hi> in publike; whoſe manly countenance, and Princely towardlineſſe amazed them more, then if they had ſeene ſome Meteor or portentous Comet: What ſhould I inſiſt on circumſtances? By a wonderfull applauſe they gaue him notice of their liking, and a quicke diſpatch of his inueſture, aſſurance of their approbation: ſo they made no more adoe, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed him Emperour, and allowed him all his prerogatiues, as if hee had beene of mature iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to challenge their proſtitution indeed. The next worke was the impriſoning of his Vnkle, or, if you will, ſequeſtring him into the former Palace where his brother appoynted him to remaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death, with a Gard of <hi>Capogies.</hi> Here he was confined, well attended, and better obſerued: For
<pb facs="tcp:193603:9"/>ſuch was his Fortune, that then <hi>Scander Baſhaw</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed his depoſure from the neceſſity of their owne preſeruation, and feare of the tumultuary <hi>Ianiſaries,</hi> who ſtill cryed after the ſonne of <hi>Achmate,</hi> and euer after (as it ſtill continues) the <hi>Viceers</hi> deale in no cauſe without his priuity and aduice; in ſo much, that when the ambitious <hi>Baſhaw</hi> propoſed the war againſt <hi>Poland,</hi> as a continuation of ſome glorious action for the honour of the <hi>Othoman</hi> Family, and renouation of <hi>Achmates</hi> charge to his ſonne in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge of their darings to defend <hi>Moldauia:</hi> hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceded, vrging, The former contract was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined betweene the Emperour <hi>Mathias,</hi> or the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and his brother, and that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Europe</hi> were more war-like, and better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided then in times paſt: to which againe <hi>Scander Baſhaw</hi> replied, as much incenſed againſt the <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> that there were many reaſons to moue the warre, and inferences of inforcement to ſet forward the enterprize.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the fleſhing (as it were) of the young Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror with noble beginnings in a plentifull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and delightſome fields, where there would bee neither <hi>Anachims</hi> nor Giants to terrifie them, nor aſperity of weather or wants to exanimate the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier. Secondly, the Countrey conſorted to their military manner of fighting, as being a kinde of Champion and vberant ſoyle, whereby their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers might haue the more roome, and their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages eaſineſſe of trauell. Thirdly, it would keepe other Princes in awe, from aſſuming a liberty to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb facs="tcp:193603:10"/>their great Lord, or preſuming that any po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer on earth ſhould be able to withſtand the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetane</hi> Army. Fourthly, if Princes did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge exaſperating wrongs, they would bee vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended and quickly made a ſcorne to inferiours. Fifthly, opportunity was not to be dallied withall, according to the ſaying of <hi>Fronte capillata pòſt eſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio calua:</hi> and now the Emperours of <hi>Germany, Rodolphus</hi> and <hi>Mathias</hi> being dead, the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> would repine againſt the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and bandy themſelues to ſet the peace of <hi>Europe</hi> in combuſtion. Laſt of all, their owne Empire began to grow populous, and the Prouinces had need of exonerating their people, or elſe ſome plague and dearth would deuoure them, without further good or profit to the Common-wealth, then choking the ayre with the ſtench of their carcaſſes, or ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling one another with thefts and robberies.</p>
            <p>To all theſe the noble <hi>Muſtapha</hi> punctually an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: Firſt, concerning the leading the Emperor to the martiall Theater, hee being ſo young, and not apprehenſiue either of glory, or reuenge; it would be imputed to the priuate humour or coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſſe of ſome priuate men. As for ſecurity in the vvarre, opinion might bee deceiued, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption abuſed: for the <hi>Maſters</hi> of <hi>Pole</hi> vvere as good horſe as themſelues: and though they had not ſuch numbers, yet were they better furniſhed &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted; and though there vvere not ſo many ſtrong Cities to batter or ſurprize, yet had they learned the cunning of trenches, with the vſe of
<pb facs="tcp:193603:10"/>great Ordnance and fortification, yea, they knew the diſcipline of a Campe, and the effect of ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems. Secondly, concerning the commodiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Countrey, to their Military diſcipline, what ſhould arrowes doe againſt ſtrong Corſlets, and Targets of defence? Beſides, they had Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebuze on Horſebacke, as well as themſelues, and what they wanted in number, was ſupplied with diſcipline and armour: as for the valour of ourna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and their obedience to their Commanders, who peraduenture were careleſſe to loſe ſuch whom they were willing to ſpare, the times were altered, and nature had taught all creatures the lawe of preſeruation. Thirdly, concerning the terrifying of other Princes, they would be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. For <hi>Rota fortunae in gyro,</hi> and the <hi>Turkes</hi> had not ſucceſſe in a ſtring; nay, what Monarchy was euer ſo eſtabliſhed, but came at laſt to a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, ſubiect in the ſame manner to diminution, as it began with augmentation? Not that I would extenuate the glory of our <hi>Ianiſaries,</hi> but from modeſt coniecture of alteration, not to bee too confident of our greatneſſe: For by experience we haue found many interceptions both at <hi>Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonium, Vienna,</hi> and <hi>Malta:</hi> wee loſt the battaile of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> hazarded <hi>Tauris</hi> and other Cities to the <hi>Perſian,</hi> were turmoyled with the rebels at <hi>Aleppo,</hi> and at this houre are affronted by the Pyrats and robberies of the blacke Sea. Fourthly, concerning reuenges, whereunto the Empire was engaged for feare of being ſlighted by others, it was queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:193603:11"/>in many caſes a worthy worke, and a tricke to deſerue as much as might be at Honours hands, but in this particular it was too too true, that from the yeere 1608. to 1620. many vſurpers had ſtarted vp in <hi>Moldauia</hi> from the ſupportation, I will not ſay corruption of the <hi>Viceers</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and therefore hee ſaw no reaſon vpon ſo ſlender mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, as the relieuing of one another, either for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or neighbourhood to raiſe ſo great a warre againſt <hi>Poland,</hi> or breake the peace, which had been ſo long continued, though the vnruly <hi>Coſſacks</hi> ſtill remayne refractary, both againſt vs and their owne Lords. Fifthly, concerning the diſſentions of the <hi>Europian</hi> Princes, the mayne buſineſſe lay remote from them, and if there ſhould be ſuch occaſion as the <hi>Triumuiri</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſerued the <hi>Romanes,</hi> the neighbour Princes would quickely vnite together againſt a publike enemy; nay, what know we, if our forces be this way gathered againſt <hi>Poland,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe mighty Nauies of <hi>Europe</hi> would not mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter themſelues and come into the <hi>Leuant,</hi> and then what could a few Gallies doe againſt ſo many goodly Ships? Laſt of all, concerning the loſſe of men, what Frince could anſwere for the ſoules of his Subiects, except the cauſe were warrantable, and the warre allowable? Ambition was no plea in Paradiſe, nor Reuenge a iuſtifiable excuſe before their God. Againe, if in the oppoſition they found as many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and as much enraged, what would then be the iſſue and finall effect?</p>
            <p>When Prince <hi>Muſtapha</hi> had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded, I was miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtred,
<pb facs="tcp:193603:11"/>and imputed rather to puſillanimity then courage, or the reſolution of an Heroicke ſpirit: wherefore they reſolued to daſh out theſe incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances, and ſuppreſſe his allegations from the knowledge of the Army, and indeed to take a cleane contrary courſe, ſo that by the conſent of the <hi>Mufty,</hi> and the principall Doctors of the Law, the war was determined, &amp; <hi>Scander Baſhaw</hi> proſtituted himſelfe before the young <hi>Oſman</hi> with humble in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, that he would be reuenged: who preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bade him riſe, and as if he thought it a paſtime, cried out, To the war: and that hee would in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, though not twelue yeeres olde, goe into the field: whereupon the <hi>Tartars</hi> were ſent for, the Cammels prouided, the Artillery appoynted, the bridges prepared, the pioners maſtered, the muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſet out, the <hi>Ianiſaries</hi> rewarded, and all things ordered to the beſt purpoſe, that might ſet forward the enterprize, and belonged to ſo great an Army, and formidable a preparation.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I am willing to touch the praiſes of the <hi>Polonians,</hi> and in no ſort to obumbrate their glory, that haue deſerued ſo well, not only for their valiant enterprizes, and ſucceſſefull victories, but for their religious care to retribute thankeſgiuing to God, that hath giuen them ſuch wonderfull meanes of preuayling: I will now tell you how o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers tell the ſtory, or adde as ſupplyment this, which is yet vntold. About the yeere 1609. one <hi>Stephen</hi> liuing with the <hi>Viceer</hi> at <hi>Conſtaninople,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a right to the Principate of <hi>Moldania,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:193603:12"/>either by fauour or preſents, had the aſſiſtance of 20000. <hi>Turkes,</hi> whereby he preuayled in the proiect: yet others impute the occaſion of ſending theſe men to <hi>Mehemet Baſhaw,</hi> who fayling in gathering vp the taxes and tallages of the Countrey, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed the <hi>Viceer,</hi> that he muſtered a great Army againſt the Sonnes of the Prince of <hi>Moldauia,</hi> whom they barbarouſly defeated and ſlew with their Vnkle <hi>Simeon:</hi> and becauſe the Sonnes of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> were reputed Baſtards, the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> by a contract from the <hi>Turkes,</hi> had the naming of a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor amongſt them, who choſe <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the younger Sonne to bee <hi>Vaiuod:</hi> which ſo diſpleaſed <hi>Mehemet Baſhaw,</hi> who was deſigned to rectifie the diſorders of this Countrey that by force of Armes he ſpoyled whom he liſt, and as it ſhould ſeeme, in deſpite of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> killed <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and ſet vp one of his owne faction; which indignity not to be indured amongſt Princes, cauſed the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> ſtill to helpe and aſſiſt theſe diſtreſſed peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; ſo that incited by the lawes of Chriſtianity and neighbourhood, beſides thoſe high motiues of princelineſſe and royalty, they thought it merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and a duty of renowne, and ſo accordingly ſupplied their wants, and tooke vp armes in their defence.</p>
            <p>Theſe warres and contentions laſted till <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was choſen King of <hi>Poland,</hi> a warlike Prince, and one that had many contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with the <hi>Muſcouites,</hi> and ſome Competitors of his owne Nation: but taking vpon him this gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:193603:12"/>hee alſo tooke vpon him the protection of <hi>Moldauia,</hi> ſo that as you haue heard, about the yeere 1618. the youthfull <hi>Oſman,</hi> Emperour of <hi>Turks,</hi> by the inſtigation of <hi>Siander Baſhaw,</hi> and the <hi>Viceers,</hi> gaue order for the muſtring vp of a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Army, conſiſting of many <hi>Tartars,</hi> the onely enemy to the <hi>Europaeans,</hi> to whom were vnited the Countreys of <hi>Dacia, Seruia, Bulgaria, Illyria, Thracia, Epyrus,</hi> and the tributary Prouinces of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> themſelues, who durſt not gaineſay the <hi>Turks</hi> offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, for feare of ſlauery, bondage, and ouer-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their Countreys, vpon the leaſt drawing back or murmuring, to bee made inſtruments of their brethrens blood.</p>
            <p>In this manner was a warlike body compoſed of 200000. who marched into the fields of <hi>Dacia</hi> and <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> where the <hi>Polacks</hi> incountred them with ſome auxiliaries out of <hi>Ruſsia,</hi> and the borders of the blacke Sea, and although they came not neere them in numbers, yet God be thanked, they ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them in valour, and noble performances: For to ſpeake without oſtentation, ſuch was the fortune of the noble <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> and the brauery of the yong Prince his ſonne, that they neuer came to any forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble incounter, but the <hi>Polonians</hi> went away with a preſent ſucceſſe, and further hope of preuailing: for which, they euer added thankeſgiuing to God, and ſolemne Proceſſion for their victories: Yet you muſt thinke, their fortune neuer grew to that height, of ſuch numbers as is reported to be ſlaine on the <hi>Turks</hi> ſide, but that they receiued reciprocall
<pb facs="tcp:193603:13"/>damages, and ſaw ſome of their owne men made the ſtuffings of graues, and the furniture of a ſlaughter-houſe: onely this is certaine, that in the yeere 1620. they gaue the <hi>Tartars</hi> an ouerthrow, as they were tranſporting their men at the nether ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers to paſſe into firmer ground, that their bodies ſtopped the ſtreame, and 20000. at leaſt were ſlaine at three ſeuerall incounters, which ſo inraged the yong Emperour, that he ſware to goe in perſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the field with all his forces, and then it may be, there might haue beene pulled on more fearefull ruines on the heads of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and their fields muſt needes haue beene heaped vp with many ſlaughtered carkaſſes.</p>
            <p>But the God of mercy and compaſsion, one way tooke pitty of theſe innocents and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and another way put a hooke in the noſe of this <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> or if you will, abated the ſtrength of <hi>Behemoth,</hi> and that by meere accident, as by theſe particulars may appeare: while the youthfull <hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> full of heate and rage, prepared to goe in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon into <hi>Bogdonia,</hi> and ſo reſolued without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to paſſe into <hi>Poland:</hi> the firſt yeere he was intercepted by a plague in the Army, and ſo they thought it vnmeet to hazard his perſon to ſuch contagion and affrighting diſeaſes. The next yeere they will haue an earth-quake to be ſo formidable at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that beſide the ſhaking of the ground, ouerthrow of houſes, and deuaſtation of Churches; certaine fearefull ſtormes terrified them more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hand-writing, that knockt <hi>Belſhazzars</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:193603:13"/>knees together. At another time, the Emperour hauing diuers <hi>Baſhawes</hi> ſonnes appoynted to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him, would needs, in a wanton iollity, goe ſport himſelfe in the <hi>Sacra porta</hi> at <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and out of his Gally threw wild-fire and ſquibs amongſt the ſhips, which ſure would haue done much harme, but that the ſailors, acquainted with the ſame, by wetting their ſailes, and other deuices, preuented the miſchiefe, offering no vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence vnto his owne Gally; yet did they returne ſome ſtones and ſquibs into the reſt: but paſſing by a lime-boat, whoſe ſmoke hindred them from deſcrying, or diſcouering the Emperor, they threw their hot ſtones amongſt the Gallies, whereof one hit him full on the breſt to his ouer-turning, as hee was laughing at the tacklings ſet on fire, and the poore ſlaues ſtripping themſelues for feare of bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Another time as he was riding on hawking, he receiued ſo ſore a fall, that the blood guſhed out of his noſe, and the company were amazed at his careleſneſſe. Another time ſporting himſelfe in the paſſage to the blacke ſea, where the riuer (as I call it) is a narrow ſtreame of 20. miles in length, beſet on each ſide of the banke with <hi>Baſhawes</hi> hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, like the pretty fabricks betweene <hi>Padoa</hi> and <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> he would needs attempt to throw a handſome ſtripling ouer-boord, which he did with that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that hee had like to haue followed him into the water, had not the Steers-man left the helme, and tooke hold of his crimſon ſatten skirts, and ſo ſtayed him; yet his Turband fell into the water,
<pb facs="tcp:193603:14"/>and the youth ſwamme to another Galley.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſome other detained him a while from his firſt ſpeedineſſe of going in perſon into the field, or augmenting his army to ſuch a greatnes, as was euer allowed to the preſence of an Emperor. But neither theſe, nor any thing elſe could coole the heat of his fury and diſpleaſure, but that hee muſt needs ſend both defiance, and threatning into <hi>Poland,</hi> that though his reuenges were procraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by diuers occaſions, yet would he come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them like a whirle-wind, and take a backward race, to runne the more ſpeedily forward: nor was this meſſage performed ſportiuely, as a cuſtome of vnkindneſſe and ill conceiued diſpleaſure between Princes, but with proteſtation and vowes, innoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and fearefull execration and othes to doe ſomething memorable for the glory of the <hi>Othoman</hi> Family: whereupon, as an intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to a more and greater miſchiefe, hee ſent <hi>Scander Baſhaw</hi> before, with a new army into <hi>Bog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia</hi> of 200000. <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Tartars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> perceiued it would be worſe and worſe, conſidering they reſolued to be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for their former loſſes, hee acquainted all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> with the perill he ſtood in, recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſome of his <hi>Coſſacks</hi> out of <hi>Hungary,</hi> placed them in the borders of <hi>Moldauia,</hi> fortified the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, and ſtopped the paſſages with new <hi>Ramparts</hi> and <hi>Barricados.</hi> Thus was an Embaſſadour ſent to <hi>Vienna</hi> to the Emperour, by way of interceſſion of a peace, or truce betweene <hi>Bethlehem Gabor,</hi> and his
<pb facs="tcp:193603:14"/>
               <hi>Imperiall Maieſty,</hi> eſpecially betweene the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> and him, that ſo their forces might be conuerted to the aſſiſtance of <hi>Poland,</hi> and repelling this common enemy of <hi>Chriſtendome.</hi> Thus was the Lord <hi>George Oſſolinski, Count Palatine</hi> of <hi>Sendomiria,</hi> ſent as Embaſſadour to the <hi>Maieſty</hi> of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> and with him Sir <hi>Arthur Aſhton Knight and Colonell, an Engliſh man,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Poland,</hi> who had audience about the 11. of May 1621. and gracious admiſſion of his Embaſſy, deliuered in the Latine tongue, both in a high phraſe, and ſo noble a demeanour, that the King with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary willingneſſe accorded to afford him a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſumme of money for the leuying of 2000. <hi>Volentiers</hi> for a Gard to the King of <hi>Poles</hi> body. And thus were the <hi>Turkes</hi> inſolent letters publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and many <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hearts opened the dores of Charity, and not onely offered themſelues to ſo good a worke, but bewailed the troubles of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> that kept the Princes within the circle of their owne vnkindneſſe, from a better and more religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous care for the generall proſperity of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But God be thanked, in the meane time, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> with the hopefull Prince his ſonne, had ſo brauely demeaned themſelues, that in foure ſeuerall incounters they ſhewed the <hi>Turkes</hi> the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of ſo ſtrong an arme, that 40000. at the leaſt ſhrunke vnder the fury of a iuſtifiable anger, and theſe Infidels ſaw plainly, that the God of <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> would propagate his Church and Religion in deſpight of miſ-beleeuers. Nor were theſe victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb facs="tcp:193603:15"/>paſſed ouer ſo ſlightly: but the King of <hi>Poland</hi> commanded generall Proceſſion by way of thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing thorow his Prouinces: and by way of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and well-deſerued triumphs, made the bonefires in <hi>Cracouia</hi> teſtifie to the world, that the God of battels had lighted them the way to ſucceſſe &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory: nor ended it ſo, but a Captain was ſent with letters to <hi>Vienna,</hi> to participate the good newes to the Emperour, who likewiſe dined with my Lord <hi>Digby</hi> (his <hi>Maieſties</hi> extraordinary Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour to the Emperour) not two dayes (being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the third of September) before hee tooke his leaue of <hi>Caeſar</hi> to returne toward <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since which time, rumour hath had ſuch vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall paſſage amongſt vs, that many men haue bin ſtartled againe with a ſtrange amazement, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo glorious a Prince, and well deſeruing an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhould be ouer clouded with a tempeſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable diſtreſſe. For many men will haue it, that vpon the laſt preuailing of the noble Prince, who was in perſon in the fields of <hi>Bogdonia,</hi> the <hi>Turkes</hi> were ſo exaſperated, and the <hi>Tartars</hi> aſhamed of ſome demiſſeneſſe imputed vnto them, that they made head againe about the beginning of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, and were againe repulſed with an Heroike violence and ſucceſſe, in ſo much that a greater computation of their numbers ſlaine then euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, reioyced the <hi>Polonians,</hi> that they grew ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſumptuous, and in a manner diſranked them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with a careleſneſſe, vvhich vvas neither ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually done, nor couertly performed, but ſome
<pb facs="tcp:193603:15"/>valiant <hi>Ianiſaries</hi> of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> and certaine <hi>Spahies</hi> which are horſemen, and were here freſh, as not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the former battell, rallyed the diſcomfited <hi>Tartars,</hi> and out of their great numbers brought a new battell in forme, and ſo gaue a freſh aſſault, with fearfull impetuoſity, vpon the ouer-confident <hi>Polonians,</hi> who, you muſt conſider, for all their former preuailings, had much diminiſhed their troups, and weakened their Batalions; in ſo much that they gaue ground; and theſe Fry of <hi>Tartars,</hi> with their accuſtomed outcry and clamours, tooke the aduantage of their retreat, and put them piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to rowt, if not to a lamentable flight, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them as farre as <hi>Podolia,</hi> with the terrour and bloody effects of a ſtrange execution, which hath raiſed ſtranger reports amongſt vs, as farre as the ſlaughter of 30000. men, beſides other cruelties and monſtrous barbarouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>In this eſtate ſtand theſe Eaſterne Countries at this houre, and feare and miſchiefe houer ouer them like a thickened cloud, ready to powre down horrid ſhowres of deuaſtation and miſery: But that God, I hope, which holdeth the windes in his hands, and rolleth vp the heauens like a ſcroll, which is ſo glorious in his workes and wonders for Iſrael, which ſent his Angell to deſtroy the Hoſt of <hi>Sennacherib,</hi> and which will preſerue the woman in the Wilderneſſe, in deſpight of the Dragons watching her, will auert his Iudgements from pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſinners, and turne theſe threatnings into <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams</hi> bleſſings, though he came of purpoſe to curſe
<pb facs="tcp:193603:16"/>the people of God: but if againe the corrupt body of our ſinnes muſt needs haue a purging, for the procuring of new health, and ſauing of our ſoules in the day of vengeance: let vs ſubmit to his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for the cure, who knowes what is better for our wounds then our ſelues, and (if need be) can powre in the balme of <hi>Gilead</hi> for our perfect reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery: otherwiſe, if they bee feſtered and rankled with wanton dalliance, furquedry, gurmundize, couetouſnes, pleaſure and eaſe, gentle <hi>Cataplaſmes</hi> will not ſerue the turne, but they muſt be cut, ſeared and cauterized: all vvhich God grant vve may pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently endure, and put into the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> hearts and mouthes, to thinke and ſay, Neither life nor death, vvarre nor peace, things preſent or to come, threatnings, nor miſchiefe, ſhall keepe or detaine vs from the hope, and future poſſeſſion of eternall happineſſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Immenſa eſt, finémque potentia Coeli</l>
               <l>Non habet: &amp; quicquid ſuperi voluëre, peractum eſt.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ouid. Lib. 8. Metam.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:193603:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
